Guide to the Melbourne Rock 'n' Roll High School Archive 1991-1998 MSS 325
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Melbourne Rock 'n' Roll High School Archive
1991-1998
MSS 325
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Scope and Content
The Melbourne Rock 'n' Roll Highschool Archive contains administrative materials, including grant applications and a student application; promotional materials including flyers, stickers and tickets for performances by associated bands; issues of Rock 'n' Roll High School Newsletter; press about Rock 'n' Roll High School including issues of Polymer News and Westinghouse Magazine; media, including CDs, audiocassettes and a 7" vinyl of recordings by bands involved with Rock 'n' Roll High School.
Historical Note
Founded in 1990 by Stephanie Bourke, a drummer and singer for band Hecate (called Litany when touring overseas), Melbourne Rock 'n' Roll High School provided a venue for hundreds of mostly female students to collaborate and learn to play rock music. Bands launched by the school include Bindi, Midget Stooges, Sourpuss, Tuff Muff and Sheraw.
Bourke began the school after her experiences teaching classical music piano to students in (mostly female) highschools, where students were interested in learning guitar, drums, keyboards, and bass and making their own music. Bourke began running a summer school from a space in East Melbourne in summer 1989. At first she was able to borrow gear and set up a band room and recording facilities, putting out the word through girl networks and employing friends as teachers, and working out some basic fees to cover costs. Bourke and others then approached the Victorian Women’s Trust and Government agencies (VicHealth) for funding, and rented a space for a permanent Rock 'n' Roll High School in 1990 at 186 Easy Street, Collingwood. The school's programs resulted in CDs, live shows, and an eventual worldwide network of musicians as Riot Grrrl emerged as a movement.
Sources:
- Shaw, Megan. (1997, December 29). "Sounds like the girls are playing up" The Age.
- Milne, Lachlan. Email correspondence, February 2012
Arrangement
The collection is divded into two series by material type. Within the series, original order has been retained.
Series I: Administrative files, Promotional materials, and Press
Series II: Media
Provenance
The collection was donated to Fales by Lachlan Milne in 2010.
Hecate (Musical group)..; Administrative records.; Fliers (printed matter); Grant proposals.; Lyric sheets.; Melbourne (Vic.).; Music |x Social aspects.; Musicians |y 1990-2000.; Newsletters.; Posters.; Riot grrrl movement.; Rock music |z Australia.; Rock music.; Rock musicians.; Women rock musicians.
- Series I: Administrative Files, Promotional Materials, and Press, 1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Administrative (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flyers and Promotional Materials (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rock 'n' Roll High School Newsletters, 1991-1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Press (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Liner notes from Melbourne Rock 'n' Roll High School Vol. 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General note
    From original ID: 325.0016. See access copy: ID 325.0019.
- Series II: Media
  Conditions Governing Access
  Only items listed under "access copies" have been preserved. Please contact a Fales archivist with questions about access.
  - Subseries A: Access Copies
    - Rock'n'Roll High School Vol. 1 (Shelf Media, Media ID:325.0019)
      Contents: Hecate - Private School, Bindi - Cheers, Protea - Limehouse, Smurfblood - Tugboat, Hecate - Rapunzel, Camden - Beauty Queern, Spot the Beast - Over the Edge, Leviathan - Eve of Execution, Blinde Spectators - Catch Me (Alone), Snodra - Sitting, Bindi - Crazybitch, Gritty Kitty - Chainsawed Emotions, Midget Stooges - Shithouse, Four - Crazy, Smurfblood - Cure Ticket, Blinde Spectators - No, Spot the Best - Body Bag
      See also: Liner notes, Box 1 Folder 5
      TRT: 57.8 minutes
      Format: CD
      Original ID: 325.0016
  - Subseries B: Originals
    - Babes in Toyland - To Mother (Catatonic, Mad Pilot, Primug, Laugh my Head off, Spit to See the Shine, Ripe, Quiet Room), undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0001)
      Format: audiocassette
    - Bindi, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0002)
    - Craw - blimey..., undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0003)
    - blinde SPECTATOR, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0004)
    - Hecate, 1995 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0005)
    - MALL, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0006)
    - Midget Stooges, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0007)
    - Sour Puss, 1995 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0008)
    - Rock'n'Roll High School - Order v. 2 - 2nd one, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0009)
    - Rock'n'Roll High School Vol. 3 Sampler, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0010)
    - Spot the Beast, 1995 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0011)
    - Spot the Beast, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0012)
    - Bindi, 1998 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0013)
    - Hecate, 1996 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0014)
    - Litany - peculiar world, 1998 (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0015)
    - Rock'n'Roll High School Vol. 1, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0016)
    - Rock'n'Roll High School Vol. 2, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0017)
    - Melbourne Rock'n'Roll Highschool Archive, undated (Box 2, Media ID: 325.0018)
      Format: DVD-R
      Contents: scanned docs, some music in digital format [per annotations]